，我是Chili
欢迎回到3D基础教程15
今天我们要讨论的是Gouraud着色
我不知道那是不是正确的读法
但是我就这样读了
所以你们最好习惯一下
你们现在应该在想Chili，Gouraud着色到底是什么
这是一个平滑着色你物体的方法
直到现在我们一直都是平面着色
如果你注意游戏里面的话，着色不都是一个个平面拼起来的
它们很好看，平滑，圆
所以我们要学习一种实现它的技巧
如果我们要平滑着色一些东西
我们会需要一些平滑的东西来着色
一个球体是我能想到最平滑的东西了
所以我们想要一个球体
我们可以直接从模型文件中读取一个球体
但是球体是个很简单的几何体
我们可以一步步生成它
这样我们就可以控制它
尤其是它的网格密度
我们生成它的方法就是
有很多种实现的方法，但我们就直接用
纬度经度模型
我们看，纬度，被角度分开这些线
然后经度，它们两个的相交就得到了很好的角顶了
然后我们可以把这个转换成3D模型
然后这些角顶就是网格的角顶
这些平面会是像正方形一样
顶部和底部，你在顶部和底部就各放一个角顶，它们是极点
然后你把这里这些连接起来
这样就不是四边形，就是单个的三角形
非常简单直接，不是很难构思
另一个实现的方法是，icosphere
icosphere就像是这样
它有个优势就是每个三角形都是一样大小的
和你用这些得到的不一样
小三角型在上面，大三角形在下面
这个更简单，这就是我们要用的方式
所以总的思想就是，用一个向量垂直向上
沿着z轴的方向
然后用一个循环旋转向量
每次增加分隔纬度的角度数量
然后对每一条纬线
做另一个循环根据经度方向旋转
然后在这个内层循环每次迭代产生一个角顶
在生成所有的角顶之后
然后生成索引来选择角顶，标记出三角形
来绘制
这样就得到了一个模型
我们的做法会跳过南极和北极
我们生成除了那两个之外的所有角顶
然后我们生成所有绕着这里的索引
除了这里弯曲的这个
连接着起点和终点的这个
所以我们没有封顶也没有封闭
我运行程序之后你就会看到了
所以让我们开始吧
我们怎么开始呢？
我们有个基础向量，朝向z轴上方，长度是半径
我们这里的这个函数Sphere的Get...下标三角形列表
给出半径，给出纬度分隔、经度分隔
得到了基础角顶或者说基础向量
然后得到纬度之间的角度
也就是 π / 纬度分隔
记得纬度是个半圆
所以是 π / 纬度分隔
经度是完整的圆
所以是 2π / 经度分隔
我们创建个vector来装角顶
我们遍历纬度
我们从1开始因为我们要跳过北极点
然后我们去到分隔数量为止
然后我们根据(纬度角度 * 当前纬度下标)旋转基础向量
这样会给我们一个纬度基础
这个是我们的基础向量
然后我们的纬度
0 1 2
我们从这里旋转到这里
在x轴，这是z轴
这个我想是从我们的角度看到的x轴
这个就是y轴
看起来有点奇怪，但是你明白什么意思了吧？
所以绕着x轴旋转到这里
然后一旦我们得到了这个基础向量
我们就把它绕z轴旋转
这就是你看到的内层循环
内层循环中，从0到经度分隔数量
我们把角顶放到列表里面
然后把它的位置设置为基础纬度绕z轴旋转（经度角度 * 当前的经度索引）
然后你得到了一个角顶
对所有除了南极点和北极点之外角顶都这样做
现在计算索引
我们遍历纬度和经度
这里有个 叫什么来着 lambda函数
来基于iLat和iLong获取角顶列表中的下标
我用它
然后我就 iLat iLong，让我画下图给你们讲下怎么回事
让我们假设我们纬度的下标是这样的
0 1 2 3 4 5 6
然后我们的经度是0 1 2 3
让我们假设iLat是1
所以从这里开始
然后iLong 是在0
所以我们从这里 (iLat, iLong)
然后我们有个 (iLat, iLong + 1)
(iLat + 1, iLong), (iLat + 1, iLong + 1)
这是四个我们需要的
然后我们就选择三个
这三个创建一个三角形
然后这三个创建另外一个三角形
注意这个弯曲的顺序
然后我们就一直这样做
这就是这里的代码做的事情
对吧？(iLat, iLong)
(+1,)， 这里(,+1)
然后(+1, +1)
把它们全都放到indices中
这里是我们放封闭部分的地方
因为我们要把最后一个经度和第一个经度封闭起来
我们没有封闭
我们也还没封顶
什么意思呢？让我们看看
这个就是没有封闭和封顶的球体的样子
通常我工作的方式是先做一个简单版本
就是先排除特殊的情况
一旦有了基线，我们就可以处理其它的部分了
尽量以最小的步伐，一步步来
我们有了基线，剩下的就是封闭和封顶了
封顶角顶很简单
基础向量和它相反的向量得到北极点和南极点
我就把它们放到角顶列表的后面
我同时记录这两个角顶的下标 iNorthPole iSouthPole
因为它们之后会有用
然后下面这里，到封闭了
我们直接封起来
(iLat, longDiv-1)
然后就可以了
这里是0，这些是起点
封闭经度的主要思路是
最后一个经度连接到第一个经度0
这样你就有了“封闭乐队”（谐音？）
“封顶粉丝”就是遍历第一个和最后一个纬度的每个经度
把它们全都连接到北极点和南极点
所以这里不是6个角顶
我们只有3个，因为基本上我们每个面只需要1个三角形
然后 封闭三角形
你还需要把北极点和南极点封闭起来
在这里搞定了，这是特殊情况
然后就可以了
这样你就有了一个完整的球体
让我们一起看看
这个就是球体的样子
很棒的球体，超棒的
很 很 什么来着 多面 尖锐 块状
它很多平面阴影，但是看起来很酷
希望你们同意
为了让它...
我的意思是游戏里面通常球体是平滑的，虽然有时是多面体
有很多种方法让它平滑
你可以直接增加几何复杂度
增加三角形的数量
把它们分成更小的块
让我们试试看
在Sphere.GetPlain给个半径
保持原来的半径
但是增加纬度的分隔到
不知道，36吧
然后经度设置为72
保存，如果我们运行，我们应该能得到更好更圆的球体
它看上去更圆更少方块了
你还是能看到这些平面
它还是很多平面阴影
但它比原来圆了
你可以继续，继续增加曲面细分，增加网格复杂度
直到它几乎完全平滑
但那会有很多几何体，很多三角形要渲染
肯定有更好的方法的
让我们假设你有个球体
理想化的球体
实际上你的几何体是三角形
它们有平面，尖尖的
我画的是二维的
在三维也是一样的意思
我们目前做的是用三角形
这些是法线，我们做些向量运算
with the direction of the light and that
allows us to determine the color shading
of that triangle now let's take a
different approach let's say this mesh
here which is an approximation of the
ideal triangle at these vertices we're
gonna store some some normals that were
derived from the ideal the ideal shape
the ideal geometry so at this point on
the sphere or on the circle the normal
is here even though a vertex is a point
in space it can't have a normal if we
were to take the normal of the the ideal
shape it would be like this so let's
take those ideal normals store them at
the vertices of the approximation now we
can use these normals and get the color
at this point on the ideal shape by
doing the normal procedure dot product
between the direction of light and the
normal and that would get us the colors
at these points and they would be the
exact colors of the ideal sphere that's
great what do we do
for all the points in between all the
points along this triangle well if you
notice something about smooth shading
you'll notice that it's a smooth
gradient from one part of the geometry
to another it's a kind of blending it's
kind of interpolation so what we can do
is we can simulate that between these
two points here we can calculate the
color at this point calculate the color
at this point and for all the points in
between we just interpolate between
those two and we'll get a smooth
gradient across the surface it's not
going to be the exact color at every
point but it's going to be a good
approximation so we calculate our light
add vertices and then we blend it we
interpolate it across basically with our
pixel pixel shader with a triangle
rasterization now the good news is we've
already done all the stuff needed for
this when we did flat shading we started
by storing the normals in the vertices
and then later on we moved on to the
geometry shader so we've already done
vertex lighting and we've already done
blending between vertex colors that was
pretty early on in when I showed you
pixel shaders so we just gotta meld
those two ideas together now the other
thing is we need to store normal data in
our vertices so we need to generate that
with our whatchamacallit our procedural
generation code for spheres but it's
actually incredibly simple because think
about it for any point on the sphere the
position vertex or the position vector
is going to be the same direction as the
normal vector right in any position
vector any geometry position vector for
a vertex is the same as the normal
vector so all you got to do is take the
geometry position vector normalize that
and you've got the normal super simple
and in fact here in sphere we've got
another function called get plane
normals and all it does is it calls get
plane gets a plane triangle and then for
every vertex
it just sets the normal equal to the
normalized position of the vertex and
there you go you've got your get plane
normals now let's take a look at goo
road shading that Mulder
alright so the Gulag shading effect is
very similar like I said the vertex flat
effect except instead of having a single
color that is going across the entire
triangle we are going to be blending so
before with the vertex flat effect we
could just assume that all the colors
were the same and we didn't have to
perform any kind of interpolation we
just took the color directly but for
this one we're gonna have to store the
color as a floating vertex or a floating
vector and then interpolate that across
the face of the triangle and then
convert that floating point color into a
integer color one thing I noticed in the
vertex flat effect just a little bit of
dumbshit for a copy and paste was that I
for the vertex data type the input
vertex I made it so that the normal
would be part of interpolation but you
don't interpolate normals it's not
something you do now not not right now
anyways
so I removed that from here but anyways
that's not important what is important
is that we create a new effect called
the GU route effect and it is going to
have a vertex type that stores position
and stores are normal and position can
you know take part in these kind of
operations here
you know you define the operations now
the vertex shader is gonna have an
output type that stores a vector e for
color and a vector E position remember
color we got to make this effect 3
because it's got to be interpolated
across the triangle when we're doing the
blending so make it a vector E each of
those components XYZ corresponds to red
green blue
and then we converted back to integers
in the pixel shader and both of these
have to be interpolated so they both
have to have the operations implemented
and then down here it's just your basic
your basic color calculation right
you've got your diffuse which is your
dot product between your rotated normal
and the direction of light and your your
gonna clamp that and you multiply it by
the diffuse color yeah that's a color
right there that's your diffuse and then
what's this again now you add the
diffuse and the ambient color vectors
you multiply across with the color of
the the object the material color you
you saturate that and make sure it's
within the range of 0 to 1 and then you
multiply by 255 and then there you go
and then you just output your position
vector times the rotation plus the
translation and yell put the color that
you calculated and there you go
you've got all your functions here to
manipulate the the light and the
material and that's it default geometry
shader doesn't do anything special and
all of the actual blending happens in
the operations for your for your vertex
type the output type and then here all
you got to do is convert from this
vector e into an integer color type and
you've returned that in the pixel shader
and there's Bob's your uncle
you've got freaking gue rod bullshit's
the scene is very simple just use the GU
rod shader it uses I think you can pass
in any kind of any kind of mesh you want
and it will apply the Guru out effect to
that you can do your rotations of the
light and the model it's all the same
and in game dot cpp we add our school
Rod scene with the get plane normals for
the sphere and here's the the final
effect and as you can see it looks
pretty gosh
sexy if I do say so myself it's a it's a
very smooth effect now one thing that
you're gonna notice here or as you might
notice and you might have noticed this
you know just from playing games in
general but although the face of it
looks very smooth if you look at the
edges you can see the actual underlying
geometry and you can see the underlying
chunkiness of the geometry so shader
effect on the face it will make things
look very smooth but it can't hide the
silhouette and the the blockiness of the
silhouette the other thing you might
notice is you can still sort of see
something like some banding here you can
see some artifacts because like I said
before it's not it's not a perfect
representation it's an approximation of
the color gradient by linear
interpolation so that Gujrat shading is
great for things like spheres but now
what if you want to render something
like a cube and you're using a garage
shading effect it's a cube it's part of
a bigger model maybe that has round
stuff on it well if you do it the naive
way of sharing all your vertices you're
gonna have to store your normals so what
normals do you give these vertices if
you give them normals pointing in this
direction like this this face is gonna
be nice and flat but then what do you do
you put your knowledge here now this guy
is going to be interpolating between
here and here you're gonna get a smooth
gradient it's gonna look it's gonna look
around it instead of looking flat like
this that's no good but if you put these
guys up here
now you this guy over see the
problem you can't share the vertices
you've got to make these faces
independent like I shown you in previous
previous videos so if using gujrat
shading and you want to do something
that has hard you're gonna have to make
those harder faces the vertices of them
independent from each other to get that
to get that hard cut off instead of a
smooth gradient so that's one issue to
be aware of now another issue is how you
generate your normals for something like
a procedurally generated sphere it's
trivial right trivial to generate these
normals but what if you have something
like a low polygon model so maybe you
generate a model of a face like this
it's very high quality it has a high
or it has you know like mathematical
curves that define it and from that you
generate a low polygon model and let's
say you've only got them the low polygon
model you only got the positions of the
vertices how do you go how do you derive
the the surface normals so that you can
smooth shade it and get something that
looks more like this and the answer is
you can't really do it perfectly because
when you go from this high model to this
low you lose information and you can
kind of fake it by you know taking the
face normals and averaging them or
something like that but it won't be
perfect so in general what you do is
when you are generating the low poly
model you also generate the normals from
the high poly and then you've got good
normals to work with and in the modeling
software you can often tweak the normals
afterwards you can drag them around and
that changes the way the shading works
on your geometry but in general you're
not gonna get a perfect effect if you
try to take a model that doesn't have
normal informations and you know
procedurally add normal information
afterwards it's possible but it might
not look as good as you would hope now
sphere is a nice piece of geometry to
test our smooth shading but I also
wanted to test it with something a
little more interesting
so I implemented loading models with
normal data so that we can load a model
that has the normal data set up for it
and get a nice smooth shaded interesting
model so we're gonna be using tiny obj
and it's terrible and I hate it
but it's what I started with and I don't
want to change
midway through anyways look at our
models here we've got bunny obj and
we've got Suzanne and Suzanne then lucky
like you normally used to you've got
your vertices you list of vertices and
this is fairly detailed model so it's
gonna have a lot of vertices yeah there
we go and then you've got another list
here of vertex normals and you'll notice
these guys one thing that's pretty
prominent from them is they're all
normalized you're not gonna see any guys
that have
a length that's not one basically so you
got your vertex normals and then after
that you've got your faces and the faces
they specify you know three vertices
that form the triangle and they specify
the index into the position vector and
the index into the normal vector so
they're independent of each other and
they're indexed independently and tiny
obj makes it hard to get that
information out but you'll see that in a
second so how do we do this well we got
to figure out how to get that normal
information out of tiny obj into our
vertices so we're gonna index triangle
list dot H and I'm adding another
function in here load normals which
loads the mesh with normals and give it
a file name it's very similar to what we
had before here with just the loading
yeah here with just load so here we're
loading the vertices and indices normals
okay so so when we whenever we basically
whenever we're putting our indices into
the index buffer we're also going to
update the normals for all the affected
vertices so I love the index struct from
mesh indices indexed at the you know the
correct indexing position and this is
normal like before I then store the the
index into my own vector the ID x dot
vertex index but it also has ID x dot
normal index and there are three of
those and that corresponds to the three
components of the normal it's it's
it's this is really
garbage interface but I will index into
my vertices at the vertex index and I'm
gonna update its normal whenever I do an
index so sometimes some normals will be
updated twice or three times
but it doesn't matter I know I'm not
gonna worry about that this is the
easiest way I could think of doing it
and that gets that information together
because basically the way objects work
are the indices and the positions the
vertex positions and the vertex normals
are stored separately but in our system
we're storing them together so we've got
to get them together and this is how we
do it and then the rest is the same so
this is I don't recommend it if
you were going to be starting your own
from scratch and you wanted a good
library I haven't actually tried it out
myself so I can't say for sure but this
one looks really nice and easy to use
obj loader the interface is super simple
you create the loader you load the file
and then you've got access to all the
messages and for each mesh you can just
index into a vertex and get its position
and get the component with the dot
notation you have to do this
freaking indexing math to get out your
freaking earth makes me mad why did I
ever pick this terrible terrible library
anyways so that is loading and if we run
this we see we've got a beautiful
beautiful baby girl
look at this lovely lovely Suzanne and
yeah works works great smooth shading
loaded are loaded our mesh can use this
to load pretty much any mesh from object
file and if it's got normals it's gonna
work it's gonna be sweet so that's gonna
do it for this video umm I recommend you
to you know play with these things play
with the procedural generation explore
on your own definitely play around with
the garage shading code because it's
something that is very important to know
about it's the basis of a lot of shading
techniques and if you want a little
challenge I got one for you
try to procedurally reconstruct the
normals for these vertices and do a
smooth shading of the bunny
see what you can do I imagine you can do
a pretty good job with a simple
algorithm to reconstruct those vertex
normals so let's see we'll see what you
get notice I'm not gonna do like a
homework solution thing for it or
anything just a little challenge for you
if you're interested I hope you enjoyed
the video if you did please click the
like button helps a lot and I will see
you soon with some more 3d fundamentals